i thought we can discuss the
gradual training that
is found in suitors
it's sometimes divided in different ways
you know
but this is the usual in 107
in 107
it begins with is it possible
to describe a gradual training a gradual
practice and gradual progress in the dump
and the buddha says yes when he obtains
a
person to be tamed he first disciplines
him thus he says come
be virtuous restrained with the
restraint of the pratimoka
be perfect in conduct and resort
and seeing fear in the slightest fault
trained by undertaking
the training precepts in some other
sutures it's also
before that you know five precepts eight
precepts so it is
overall that's the first step
of virtue taking on the precepts
but i think the seeing fear in the
slightest fault
being able to recognize a fault and then
yeah well it's when it says uh
restrained by the rules of patamoka
like the the rules that pertain to
practice not not kind of the rules they
were pertaining to like a
social circumstances at the time uh they
all can be boiled down
into eight precepts
or ten if you wanna forsake the the
handling of money and gold and so on
which means it's not just for the monks
it's for anybody who wants to practice
obviously it was it was presumed
by wearing robes you want to practice so
that's what we'll be addressing the
marks but even if you don't wear the
robes today you want to practice the rules of
today you want to practice the rules of
patty mocha apply to you
not technically but as in the spirit of
eight precepts yes that's what whenever
the buddha would speak
in the context outside of the like a
monk sangha
speak about the virtue he would talk
about you know like the eight precepts
the wise man of the old
used to you know used to live by eight
presets all the time that's why they had
such a
long life span and so on um so
eight precepts is the bare minimum for
uh
beginning of of that uh self taming self
sense restraint the discipline the
discipline exactly yeah
it's not like if you're a disciple then
there's the discipline
exactly yes yes exactly yes if you're a
lay follower which means the one who
trails behind
out of devotion that's where the five
precepts are
means they keep you from behaving like
an animal
and you're making merit and hopefully it
will contribute towards a better birth
but if you're the one who sees himself
as as the one who practices the dhamma
the eight precepts are not negotiable
that is the the bare minimum the basis
and that's the very first thing so you
can substitute there
come here because say you want to
practice okay come here
this is the discipline you have to take
on
and when you take on that discipline you
need to start seeing the danger in the
slightest fault
now that can be taken neurotically and
probably would
will be initially like but that's that's
fine you you you get used to the neurotic
you you you get used to the neurotic
aspect of it so you'll still be bothered
by neurosis
but you still remain seeing the the
value of that discipline
and the fear of breaking it so
in a way if if you're if you're writing
about breaking the precepts
that neurosis that fear will actually
protect your discipline
so it's like hydrotype of fear and shame
of wrongdoing
so you're afraid because of all the you
know well it will it will undo
your very striving things that you want
to develop
through your practice can only be
developed on the basis of discipline
and here you are willingly eroding that
discipline through your choices to break the rules
through your choices to break the rules
so
you start contemplating on the dangers
of doing that
and then naturally you feel afraid of
doing it
and that's why you won't do it that's
why you won't be careless about it
if you're not afraid that's when people
become careless because you stop
paying close attention because there is
no fear motivating you
they kind of just jump to the
getting rid of the vagina parts i'll go
to the vagina
yeah well i work my way the other way
i'm sure
if you you know you i'm sure you can
find an article
or a teacher that will say yes you can
do it you can bypass everything the
buddha said and go straight to john
apart and then the jhana the results of that
and then the jhana the results of that
ghana
fulfill all these other factors makes
you restrained
sorts out your regards yourself sure
sure yeah well that's the common kind of uh
yeah well that's the common kind of uh
misconception of even people that keep
the precepts
they don't necessarily see the direct
value of it they don't expect
like they don't see how is this
helping me tame myself in that sense
that to what extent am i developing
through keeping the precepts they do it on
keeping the precepts they do it on
account of
you know faith culture tradition
whatever meditation group they're part
of they might do it on a kind of
external circumstances motivating them
to be
restrained and keep the priesthood
because it's a good thing and so on
universally speaking
but deep down they still hold the view
that all these random things that they
do
will then somehow magically
contribute to the special experience of
a jhana
or enlightenment and when that happens
the work's done so they don't see
basically in other words a direct work
that they can do through their own
choices and developing the right context
they will
inevitably have to result in ghana and
enlightenment they just do random work
that then they hope will produce the
experience of ghana or enlightenment and then they
of ghana or enlightenment and then they
won't have to do any work because
they're enlightened
anyway this let's go into the second
step he says
once that person has a
perfecting virtue the uh
the buddha disciplines him further
guard the doors of your sense faculties
on seeing a form with the eye
do not grasp at its signs and features
since if you were to leave the eye
faculty and so on unguarded
evil unwholesome states of covetousness
and grief might invade you
practice the way of its restraint right
so that's already the um
you know what we call colloquially in
our talks like the peripheral awareness
so you don't grasp the signs and
features of that which is seen
not like you don't see anything
so the the signs and features of that
which you
of a sense object you experience through
your senses they're always peripheral
you don't see signs and features like
when you look at the signs that says
stop you see the letters you see the color
you see the letters you see the color
you see the shape but the significance
of do not
pass this line you specifically don't
come here
stop there that's not in the sign yet
you see that
when your eyes see the sign those are
the features of that sign the
significance of it
because meaning so the meaning sure the
meaning the significance the signs the
feature the nimitz
basically and the reason i'm saying that
is because often that practice of sense
restraint is is kind of uh conflated with this
is is kind of uh conflated with this
view of beating the sense down
like not looking not looking not
touching no not breathing nothing
nothing just just
just just compress it all not see
anything but that still you're not
seeing the significance of that
the signs and features of what you're
doing you're not seeing
and that's where you need to start
basically recognizing
the sensory strain to be are you
restraining senses sure
beforehand as we said before before you
do
actions you decide you already know
whether it's going to be
rooted in version greed and so on and
then if you know then
they truly agreed you don't do it but
now say sometimes things surprise you
pop up pressure arises
that can become an ill will or
sensuality but now you have a choice of that which
but now you have a choice of that which
you have seen
you have a choice whether you're
choosing to dwell mentally
on the signs and features that are
suitable for increasing of passion in
regard to it
or the signs and features of they're
also both there
it's just what you choose to attend or
the signs and features that are not
suitable either way pressure has arisen you can't
either way pressure has arisen you can't
undo that
you've seen things so you realize okay
like i'm not in control of these eyes
only relatively speaking i can sort of
foresee as much as i can and prevent
you know things that are suitable for
lust or aversion to arise
for me to see and so on but inevitably
things will happen because the organs
are still there untamed
and when that does happen that's when we
say you need to be able to allow things
to endure
without breaking your discipline that's
the order that's why you have the
discipline first
without like floating with breaking of
the rules because you see the danger of
it
and now without losing the context of
the signs and features of that which
pressures you
and it's on that level of signs and
features of things that pressure you
that mind either delights in centrality
or tries to reject and get rid of the
discomfort and that's the root of the whole problem
and that's the root of the whole problem
so if you were to just
be restraining your senses correctly
it's it's kind of
well it's effortless you don't need to
be beating your eye down
you know cutting your ears off and some
so so you never experience the object
that might cause
pressure of lust or disagreeability to
arise in you
all you need to do is make sure when
your eye does see is do here
you don't dwell delight accept
welcome entertain
the signs and features of what you've
seen that are that are basically making
loss to increase so the sign of the
beauty the sign of agreeability the sign of
the sign of agreeability the sign of
non-danger
the sign of the sign of friendly
homely non-threatening all these things
all these significances are the sign of
sensuality because if people were to truly see the
because if people were to truly see the
danger of sensuality
none of that would ever be seen ever
again as friendly suitable
acceptable pleasurable for me it would
be seen like an ember
like a picture of burning embers well
you can also see it
with both those significances and what
you know what you used to see it as
that's what i mean the significances are
there it's not like i must remove these
significances of pleasure no no
i must stop entertaining them
and look for the other significances
that are equally there that i'm that
i've been ignoring out of my habits
of welcoming lust so can you i can look
at the beautiful parts which increases
lastly i can look at the ugly parts
which will calm things down but not for
the sake
of getting rid of the beautiful parts or
for the sake of getting rid of the
pressure that's not on you your eye is pressured
that's not on you your eye is pressured
and your eye wants the parts that are
beautiful all you need to do is just keep
all you need to do is just keep
projecting
the context of non-beautiful and
threatening and dangerous
and keep it there and it will always
prevail because it is more fundamental
context that's what we would say in beautiful if
that's what we would say in beautiful if
you develop your mind you'll be able to
see the ugly
in the beautiful not change the
beautiful into ugly
it's still the same beautiful the same
beautiful significances
and you see them as ugly through them
you see the ugly
you see the threatening you see the
danger because i do not
grasp grasp at its significance yeah
don't take it up
don't welcome it don't entertain it
because if you get so it's there the
significance is there
you take it up and you won't take it up
if you start attending the the
significances that you don't want to
take up
the significance of danger
dissatisfactory you should grasp
those the significance of danger yeah
sure because you know you don't grasp at its
because you know you don't grasp at its
signs and features
of the of the of the thing that caused
you lustful yeah since if you were to
leave the eye faculty
unguarded yeah evil unwholesome states
coveted might invade you but you you so you're
might invade you but you you so you're
saying
the other signs and features yeah like
you don't start neutrally you don't
begin your practice where you have this
equal choice of beautiful and ugly
you begin by being fully gripped
pressured taken up welcome entertained of the
taken up welcome entertained of the
beautiful
so your sense restraint begins by not
doing that
so don't grasp those features and then
the other features will become more
apparent and yeah that's you then by all means
and yeah that's you then by all means
grasp the the feature of ugly
stick to it and it will like develop
this passion into the other hand
uncertainty but those features are not
visible because of the
automatic grasp of lust automatic grasp
of getting rid of the discomfort
when you're touched by painful automatic
grasp of distraction when you're touched
by
neutral feeling
because yeah grasping at its signs and
features means in the beginning
it means unguarded you know you you're
completely yeah there is no more garden there
yeah there is no more garden there
straight into it so you guard your
senses by maintaining the context
they will basically make you uh
abstain from just habitually grasping
onto the beautiful aspects of what's
given to you
and that pertains to any given sense
and in that sense you won't be that's
what i mean like you will never be able
to welcome
and delight with lust
the significance of um
danger in sensuality that needs to be
developed that's why you cannot have lust towards
that's why you cannot have lust towards
being free from sensuality that's
inconceived that's contradiction in
terms but you will develop those signs and
but you will develop those signs and
features
by not grasping that which is suitable
for grasping
sensuality signs of beautiful welcoming
it entertaining it giving in and trying
to get rid of it
so that's like the underlying tendency
don't they don't underlie everything
they cannot underlie everything if
underlying tendency to a lust
can underlie everything you won't be
able to become another hunt
so you only need to abandon things that
are underlined by underlied by lust
aversion delusion
don't grasp to them signs and features
that are then revealed through not
grasping you can't grasp in the same sense you
you can't grasp in the same sense you
can't delight and lust after ghana and
that's exactly how you enter janna
by fully withdrawing yourself from signs
and features that are grasped
with lust for lust for increasing of
their loss you're the only signs and
features that can be grasped
yeah that's where the grasping is yeah
last full aversion and delusion yeah
so you don't grasp that and then by all
means try and grasp the signs of ugly sure
try and grasp the signs of ugly sure
there's just be mental cultivation of
other you can't grasp it with lust but you can
you can't grasp it with lust but you can
do it with effort
and and and discernment oh no this is
worth of keeping in my mind
these signs and features these limiters
are worth to be developed and adhere to
because they result in dispassion
everywhere else
so the third step so to speak
the bhikkhu guards doors of his sense
faculties then the tatargata
disciplines him further can be could be
moderate in eating reflecting wisely you should
in eating reflecting wisely you should
take food neither for amusements nor for
intoxication nor for the sake of physical beauty and
nor for the sake of physical beauty and
attractiveness but only for endurance
and continue continuance of this body
for ending discomfort
and for assisting the holy life
considering thus i shall terminate old feelings
thus i shall terminate old feelings
without arousing new feelings
i shall be healthy and blameless and
shall live with comfort
recover the food thing in many other
folks but yeah you just need to keep the
purify and sustain the right motivation
the reasons for you you have to eat
it's not optional that's the whole point
of that that's why you need to
be moderate and reflect on it not don't
think that
being moderate as an elite half of this
constitutes being moderate in eating
i'll eat half of what i want to eat no
that's basically asceticism and more
often than not it's misguided
you are moderate in eating by not losing
the context of the right reasons for
your eating
and that's exactly what the suit
describes how you moderate in eating
not by eat every third muscle that
you've taken
no you're moderating eating by not
eating for the reasons of beautification
by not eating for the reasons of
enjoyment by not eating for the reasons
of
of distraction and central attraction
but by eating for the reasons of
sustaining the body getting real
discomfort so that i can practice
and that motivation is something you you
can choose to keep in your mind or
ignore so if you keep that motivation in the
so if you keep that motivation in the
mind you won't have to worry about
overeating or under eating doesn't
matter you eat
for the sake of getting rid of
discomfort and you eat
you know for the sake of being alive
because often moderation and eating gets
conflated with you know
i eat 20 percent and and and i reach i
fulfill that thing
no you haven't you're still equally
ignorant of your motivation behind
eating you still you do you see that you're not
you still you do you see that you're not
eating or the enjoyment
eating for the second german is still
there but you're just reducing it to 20
percent it's still the same centrality doesn't
it's still the same centrality doesn't
matter if it's 120
essentiality is there
or are you really clear about the
context behind your eating
on account of which you're eating and
where that context is rooted in
what are your intentions for taking this
food is it just because you really crave
the taste
because it's it's it's like nutritious
for you you know that for a fact
what is it do you know that do you see
that do you see why you are eating when
you're reading
do you feel hunger when you read them
do you worry about oh hey they have no i
want to have that
oh but if somebody takes that i will not
have it again all of that already it's
obvious ah there you go so you're not eating for
ah there you go so you're not eating for
the right reasons
if there is any form of passion in
regard to food you're not eating for the
right reasons which means
you need to be dwelling contemplating
and discerning
those reasons more clearly further not
just okay i will not eat ever again which is
okay i will not eat ever again which is
like you know
i can untie this knot so i just cut it
that's usually people's take on this oh
just don't eat it don't eat it if you don't
don't eat it don't eat it if you don't
need to eat it
if you think you'll be fine without
eating it fine don't eat it
but don't eat it because i can't figure
out where my motivation is rooted
that's throwing away the baby with the
barf wood
because that is what a practice is
rerouting your motivation correctly
rerouting yeah because it's again you
begin by eating out of centrality
beautification craving to get rid of the discomfort so
craving to get rid of the discomfort so
you're not eating with a clear mind
oh i'm eating because there is hunger
when i finish i stop eating
and particularly like from that point of
view eating is quite a chore doesn't
matter what you eat
having to eat having to feel heavy
afterwards for a bit
you know having a food say that's all
quite nuisance
all the time and you see it for what it
is a necessity a chore
but and as you do that
you're going to have those moments you
want to eat more you want to
well exactly yes but even if you have
those moments
if you sustain the context of eating for
the right reasons all those moments will
disappear it's like like that similarly given for
it's like like that similarly given for
samadhi but it's the same principle like
heating up a pan you're going to have
moments of
you know wet drops of this or this
falling onto it but if the pan is hot
sufficiently hot enough none of the none
of that will linger on the pan it will
evaporate instantly or or pretty quickly
instantly or or pretty quickly
so as you mean don't worry to try to
like micromanage
i'll take every second dish and not from
a person on the left side of the road
that's basically
like giants complete kind of skewed
getting all completely wound up because
they didn't know how to approve the lust
so what they were doing they were trying
to control the circumstances and just
rattle themselves through like
constantly changing the requirements of
the circumstances
but that means you're looking at a
completely wrong place
you'll still be eating with lust even if
you're shunning the bait you're doing it
with lust
lustfully you don't want to engage with
lust
but you can't sustain that because
sooner or later you have to eat
and even if you don't eat if you die you
died without
revealing the true motivation behind the
centrality so you threw away the baby
so after that the buddha disciplines
the bigger further comeback would be
devoted to wakefulness
during the day while walking back and
forth and sitting
purify your mind of obstructive states
and then it goes into the you know first
watch of the night the second one
well again we did that in the last few
talks didn't we the overcoming
hindrances and stuff
like all like the liability to last that
liability to aversion
you see that that passage is very
commonly very often found in suitors or
you purify your mind
but how many contemporary practices you
find teaching you how to purify your
mind and
just tell you focus on your nostrils do
this be aware of what you're touching
what you're feeling
but how is that purifying your mind of
obstructive states
oh i don't know i just do this and i
hope nothing arises in my mind they will
be obstructive
but you're not purifying it you're just
trying to prevent it
trying to get rid of it so
that's why the purification you can't
just start with purifying your mind
because you won't even see your mind to
begin with
let alone the obstruct the states that
are obstructive for the mind
so you need to be well restrained with
discipline
you need to be you need to be celibate
you need to see the danger in these
faults then you need to be guarding the sense
then you need to be guarding the sense
faculties not grasping
not not welcoming entertaining the signs
and features that will be
increasing last increasing aversion and
so on
then you need to be moderate in eating
that's another practice
that you do on top of these things you
don't just start being moderate and
eating because again as i described it's
because again as i described it's
moderate anything it's not about a
quantity of
bread you ate it's about clarity of the
motivation behind your eating
and for most people that's completely
invisible because most people don't even
keep their precepts
most people are not salad most people
live with mind wet with centrality
most people don't get their sense
factors correctly they don't even see
the signs and features
when they hear about god in the sense
faculties they think i must not see the
eyes and
the phones with my eyes and then just
try to beat down the eyes when they do
see the forms
but that's not disciplining it that's
just trying to get rid of it kill it off
but if you do all these things that we
went through then yeah you will see
the clarity of the mind there protected
through the guarding of the senses
through the knot
through the um through the sustaining
the the context in regard to that
gateway for last and non-reason last and if you
for last and non-reason last and if you
say no fine i sustain that i'll protect
that if you're doubtful okay so this is how
if you're doubtful okay so this is how
this obstruction could enter me
and that's that whole talk we did on the
on the liability
was it uprooting versus management that
was the talk i think
the difference between uprooting and
just managing
so you being watchful regardless of what
you do throughout the day
means mind staying with that which is
the priority
so it's not about i have to go and do
that or i have to do this
or i have to stay here all of that is
secondary you will be going there and doing that
you will be going there and doing that
and staying here but the primary thing
is
i stay here guarding the gateway
towards my mind so there are no
obstructions for it that's the sole task
i have
task that i have generated and outlined
clearly for me now
on account of discipline guiding the
sense faculties
being moderate careful with motivation
in eating and now i see it clearly
this is the gateway where the
obstructions obstruct me and when they
don't obstruct me if i don't allow them
to
yeah now now you're guarding yeah
you're guarding it you're not fighting
you're not changing you're just sitting
at a gateway as a guard
and oh no you cannot enter you are in a
position to do so
because you built it up and the gateway
is basically that like one entrance into
the city that's completely walled around
and the wall around is your discipline
the wall around is your sense restraint
and seeing the danger in the slightest
fault
the behavior has been purified for
before beforehand as the wood would say
the wall has been built no wall doesn't
matter if you have a gate
you can sit at the gate and there is no
wall around it so you're not guarding
you're guarding the gate maybe
which nobody's interested in everybody
wants to go to the city
now that's why the whole like sila and
celibacy is not optional
if you want to practice if you want to
be a virtuous lay person and stay a lay
person then yeah you can keep the five precepts
then yeah you can keep the five precepts
and be generals but that's not what
we're talking about
in this talk at least so after he's
um he's disciplined in being devoted to
wakefulness
the buddhist says further kambeku be
possessed of mindfulness and awareness
again it's kind of saying the same thing
well it's it's like uh composing that
same wakefulness even further
so like like bringing that that context
that you have developed that that
god guard post that you are clear about
intensifying even further now not
through focusing meditation or practice
just being even clearer about it to the
point of you don't need to sit for half
an hour and like you know calm yourself
down whether you're extending your arm while
whether you're extending your arm while
you're extending your arm whether you're
walking talking going to the toilet
eating even these like immediate things
that you do that the mind does not
necessarily pick on
and doesn't need to pick on in the
beginning even now you're not picking on
them it just means that even while you're
it just means that even while you're
doing that that context
that god post is so clear you are there
you're not abandoning that one
job that you have protect the mind from
the obstructive states
whether walking extending put in the
robe even these little quick things
that you do but see at what stage you do
that and the reason why i pointed out is
and the reason why i pointed out is
because many people would start the
practice with that because
thinking focusing on my hands while i'm
touching is doing that no there is no focusing
is doing that no there is no focusing
there is just
developing of the context to the um
unshakable extent be celibate see the
danger in the slightest fault
guard your sense faculties be clear
about the motivation in regard to your
eating and do not allow yourself to eat
out of the unwholesome motivation
watchful and then you will know what
satisfacing is like the similar for cook
is like the similar for cook
who feeds the king his dishes and then
watches him
and sees oh he didn't take that he took
a lot of that he picks on limiters
of king's preferences and he pays
attention to significance of it
so next time he prepares more of that
which he picked so many times
and he's killed in reading limiters
that's it that's all to it
and then the other cook doesn't pick on
any limiters
and he just keeps cooking the same thing
for king and he doesn't even eat it and
then the king fires him
sends him to the dungeon so you want to
pick the limiters of your mind as well
what is your mind inclined to pick on
that before you gave in to the inclining
that's it so signs and features need to
be discerned in the background
peripherally it's not something you can
stare at
because there are always signs and
features of that which you're staring at
seeing the mind so that's well seeing
the mind you can't see the mind as
an object of your senses but you can
discern it peripherally and know it
that's the whole principle behind it
through this gradual
yeah practice rounding up building up
the wall setting on the gate
and and guarding it he practices full
awareness the next step is once he's accomplished
the next step is once he's accomplished
in mindfulness
and full awareness at a target term
uh disciplines him further can't pick a
resort to a secluded resting place
the forest the root of a tree a mountain
do not dwell in company
but then and then it goes and then he
resorts to a secluded
physical seclusion we did talks on that
as well and
then he and he abandons the injuries the
ban is the hindrances
right he continues the same you want to
be free from hindrances
which is a prerequisite for entering the
genre you need to be dwelling with your um
you need to be dwelling with your um
mindfulness and recollecting necessarily
established you want to have that established you
you want to have that established you
need to be well watchful all the time
you want to have that accomplished you
need to be
guarding no you need to be moderated in
eating didn't they then you need to be
guarding your sense though then you need
to be
celibate and restrained by the virtues
of patamorga so in other words you want
to enter janus
start being celibate here and now
so you realize janas as we often say
are the establishments of mind that come
as a result
of your purification and the lifestyle
not a magical experience they will then
take care of your lifestyle
for you which is what people hope and to
janna i'm enlightened
now everything is fine no jhana is
basically the last
symptom positive symptom
of you healing up everything that needs
to be healed any wound of lust
aversion distraction and
that's what every giant formula says
dwell secluded removing the grief
and concern in regard to the world
abandoning the hindrances
quite secluded from these unwholesome
states the pleasure of seclusion is born
you feel safe and then he enters in
abide in jhana
not like he enters and abides in jannah
and that's why he secluded
no he secluded himself from unwholesome
states jhana is the result of that
and that's what he would have said that
is a divine abiding when the target's
mind is in ghana
whether he walks eats goes to the toilet
whatever he does
it's divine
so you can live in ghana
yeah that mind that context that mind is
so purified the mind's purified the
senses were guarded
the body has been the senses have been
tamed and basically
kept within the walls the the guard post
has not been abandoned
you have not been delighting in things
they would be making last increase
um non reason last increase uh and um
non um normally non reasonable manifest
and so on
so now what you have left is just the
the kind of
the recognition of the nature of things
and uh
you haven't been given in to that which
makes hindrances overwhelm you
so you you basically not being
overwhelmed by the hindrances anymore
you are freed from them now if you
abandon your celibacy abandon your your
guarding of the
the senses abandon your moderation
meeting as the buddha say
you fall off from the jhana in the
sutras or if circumstances change to such a
or if circumstances change to such a
great extent
they just everything becomes too
unbearable like in case of severe
illnesses and so on
where you haven't abandoned your virtue
but you can't spend your time
you know guarding the gate post because
you're all remember pain half conscious
half unconscious
dying basically your guts rotting and
something like that then you might fall
away from ghana
but if your jana has been developed
beforehand even then you would not
necessarily fall away from jhana as all
the uh the irons that could obtain jan as it
uh the irons that could obtain jan as it
will were able to endure this insane
amount of discomfort and pain because of
the janus
so the pains they would be overwhelming
a normal mind were not painful for them
because of the jaundice that they've
developed but important thing you cannot stress
but important thing you cannot stress
that enough is
china is the seventh whatever
step there the result of all of this
gradual development that
literally in contemporary buddhism today
is
almost everything is bypassed and you
get to jhana first
and it's like how convenient is that
whereby where the actual work even for the jhana
where the actual work even for the jhana
is you bypass all of that
and when people say oh well banter
didn't the buddha enter jana
spontaneously well he didn't he was under the root of
well he didn't he was under the root of
a tree quite secluded from centrality
he was probably i don't know how old he
was but he was probably not sexually
active at the time
he was probably not chasing senses and
so on he was a kid
which means his mind was not turned
towards sensuality which means he's
abiding even without a jhana was
relatively pure he didn't have
sensuality and he'll will in his mind
having been quite secluded from that for
a while that time when he sat under the
tree waiting for his father his mind
developed that pleasure and account of
seclusion and that was dijanna
but he didn't really know the value of
it at a time
so then later on when he thought what if
there were the way for enlightenment
and he reasoned and said yeah that
probably is
so let me do it oh i can't do it because
like i'm overwhelmed by the physical
pain of this dying body that i've
tortured to the point of death
so let me eat something let me regain my
health and then i'll do it and he did it
so it's still the same process
it's still the same steps the jhana was
the result of withdrawal
if you get your java spontaneously it
can only happen for one reason
you've been thoroughly withdrawn from
sensuality on account of your efforts
and guarding the senators faculties
so what are the chances of that
happening accidentally
well zero to none who can accidentally
withdraw themselves from sensuality and
see the peril of the danger in sense
objects and
and lust and abandon it it's virtually
impossible because your whole being your whole
because your whole being your whole
existence is in that direction for
pleasure and to avoid pain that's the
definition of
of human realm of any realm
guided by by craving in regard to
feeling the fundamental principle behind
dukkha so you withdraw yourself from that you
so you withdraw yourself from that you
don't have to worry about janus
that is john we draw her from that
you don't have to worry about a
technique or a method which
incidentally you will not find in the
sutures
or you will find the method there it is
method is is
is celibate eight precepts guard in the
sense those
moderating eating danger in the
slightest fault watchful
clear awareness gianna
you don't need motorola method and
actually i told you that before like
what 20 something years ago when i started
20 something years ago when i started
practicing started reading the suitors
he was summoner palace sutter
i remember i was reading it and he was
he has the similar passage there anybody
describes that it's a similar creative
training and i remember reading it at the time
and i remember reading it at the time
and he was all like yeah yeah this is
great but i still had the views back in the in
but i still had the views back in the in
the early days
like 99 2000
uh that because you know or everything
else you read about buddhism is about
these techniques and experiences in
jhana one giant ii and enlightenment
and you have all these preconceived
notions about what enlightenment is so
with all that still being in my mind
i was reading suta and he was like kind
of yeah but come on tell me exactly
what i do for that jhana and for that
enlightenment as if everything else i read up to that
as if everything else i read up to that
point was not exact enough
well it wasn't exact enough because i
expected more
i wanted wanted something more focused
more particular
especially but then if you actually
start thinking about it as well wait
have i
have i have i fulfilled the first step
have i fulfilled the second step
have i well let me fulfill these steps
and then if i need something for
focusing then i'll ask
for focusing but then you realize if you
fulfill all these other steps
you will have the jhana in the same
sense they would have said like a like a
was it a hand sitting on her eggs
even if she doesn't wish for her chicks
to pass out safely they will cause she
did the work of sitting and keeping the
eggs warm so if you fulfill all these steps
warm so if you fulfill all these steps
perfect your virtue perfecting the
danger of slightest fault
watchfulness moderate and eating you
will have jannah you will have
this passion it's not a matter of
oh i did everything right but i still
don't have it no if you don't have it
means you haven't done everything
anything right or
not sufficiently right enough that's
what we say it's impossible to not have
results if practice has been undertaken
if practice has been undertaken
correctly so that's why you use that to
review yourself as well
other results to show flow like as as we
used to chant in the temples back in the
day
uh how well am i spending my life will i
be ashamed
when questioned by my companions in holy
life say if i'm
dying and my companions come to
interrogate me and see if i'm another
hunted how much this passion as they
used to do today people don't do that
but back in the day there was a norm
let's go before he dies and see what he
understood i mean how many suttas you
got that in
and then you use that oh so if one
question on my deathbed
am i another hunt actually oh i better
become another
so you use that to make make yourself
strive even more because
if you strive rightly you would have to
be an arahant or at least underground
you can't say that that but no no my
friends in holy life i have guarantee
you 100 percent fulfill buddha's instruction
100 percent fulfill buddha's instruction
but i'm not even a sort of
that is impossible inconceivable
that is like to say oh i've been living
in this desert and the sun for 50 years
of my life
but these clothes are still wet
miraculously that's impossible they
would have to dry
so you use that like okay so is there
this passion
is there proper seclusion from
hindrances from unaries and hindrances
to arise
do you see them free from that as well
develop clarity in regards to that
you're developing credit in regard to ghana
ghana
so there is a method just not the method
that most people would expect
or want not the method
you want but the method you need that's
it yeah exactly
the method everybody needs